watch your breath put your mind at your
nose watch your
breath e
in picture of
him with sunlight pouring in Golden
sunlight like molten gold like oranges
deep
color
e e
you can look out the window and see blue
sky e
and picture your teacher sitting in
front of
you your own heart teacher whoever that
is e
and just stay content in their
presence not doing anything not saying
anything just sitting in a golden room
with with your teacher quietly
silently in each other's presence
the object of this this meditation is
the feeling
being in their
presence e
come back to their
then slowly come back to this
s can you open your
eyes so um
yesterday we left it at
uh yesterday we left it uh s
junda which was the first uh cook in the
road
uh and uh a couple more comments about
that we said that uh first starting to
meditate s Joka was triggered by what I
mean what was the impetus for
that yeah learning from your teacher
okay we can say you could call the six
Powers maybe you could call them the six
imp or
something uh
impetuses okay but it's what got you to
uh do your first meditation you have a
post
okay so we're on the first B in the road
on the
left uh the Mark got his two instruments
waiting right and that's uh ginda
meaning that's a point where you first
have some continuity on the
uper that's achieved by a different
impotence called s to say
s to S to so that's as opposed to okaya
means learning and then SAA means
contemplation and that's part of a
three-fold educational process in
Buddhism called
tum
say so in in ancient times uh
traditional method of learning was first
uhti which means you listen to teachers
instructions right then SAA means you go
home and you think about them it's
called
contemplation so the difference between
Tia and S Tia is you get the
transmission from your teacher in a
classroom uh they they give you the
hearing and then SAA means you go home
and you start thinking about it so SAA
is a self motive you're starting to get
self motivated it's SAA is where the
line between s where you start uh
policing yourself and and and doing your
study at home on yourself by yourself
okay uh so the second by the time of
this
uh first B in the road on the left uh
Number Nine by the time of number nine
there you are self running okay you're
your your meditation is going you're at
home you're not at the classroom anymore
and and it's running on your own okay so
that's why it's called
s by that time the impetus that's
keeping you running is the is your own
practice at home home practice and I
think home practice is one of the things
that most attracted me about Buddhism
when I first met it in India I think the
idea that a lot of the how do you say
you know I grew up in in a church and
and you you only practiced on
Sunday uh for a brief period maybe an
hour and it was very beautiful and it
was very moving and I loved it very much
I still like it but what attracted me
when I first met the Tibetans was that
you could set up your own altar in your
house and you didn't have to have an
intermediary between you and the boss uh
you know you could uh do your own
practices and you could do your own
rituals at home and uh so some
sa in this context means you are now on
your own at home practicing and um in
most of these practices until you get to
the point where you can do your practice
at home uh self motivated to be
self-motivated uh you won't succeed okay
you you you need to get to the point
also your yoga has to get to the point
where you are self- policing you know
you have to get to a point where you
don't have to go to a class every day
you know it's good to go to a class it's
really really good to go to a class and
you get a lot of new ideas and you get a
lot of input but but pretty early in
your practice you have to become self
running right do you remember talk
s which came after s which came after
n which came after
[Music]
what do I
do uh first one Le means you should be
in a place where it's easy to find
honestly attained these are the
qualities of a good meditation spot oh
okay we did them a long time
ago uh
so means
means you should be able to find
resources for your
practice and it and they should be not
ill gotten they shouldn't involve
violence or dishonesty towards another
person or creature okay so your this are
just basic meditation support system
should be
a place where you you you are you have
food and you have things that are not uh
stolen or or killed or
okay then the second one
was I think n is uh the place should be
a good place meaning
what it should have been blessed by the
presence of holy beings
okay or at least the text said shouldn't
have been cursed
by uh people who broke their vows there
or or caused skism in the sa for example
there or some kind of bad event there it
shouldn't be a place where something bad
came down uh so the place you choose for
your meditation should be a place if you
can find a place which has been blessed
by the presence of other retrea like uh
like I was in Mongolia doing some
practice
and and I was in a Hermitage in the
mountains and people have been doing
meditation there for hundreds of years
and you could feel it right so they say
at least avoid a bad place okay I think
in America we're mostly new places now
like diamond mountain is just getting to
feel different but it it'll take time
it'll take a couple of generations maybe
so
SAS a good place a good a good area in
the sense of
what shouldn't be too
cold shouldn't be too hot you know you
should have hot water uh toilet should
work you
know but mainly it's that it shouldn't
be out of the range of comfortable
living of a human being it shouldn't be
so cold that you get sick it shouldn't
be so hot that you can't
concentrate then we were I was talking
about
to what's to
uh that was included in the last one
yeah he said correctly uh it shouldn't
be a place where you have Bears breaking
into your cabin scorpions calling all
your
bra do means good friends right should
you should have good meditation
companion and and what did this mean
yeah who
said yeah they should be heavy weights
okay it the text said looks like Mafia
from the corner of your eye you know you
walk into a restaurant there's a mafia
guy there and you you I was in a rest I
was in a tea house in Japan and the
yakuzi guys walked in and you don't go
like this you know you you drink your
tea and you're kind of
like you watch them but you don't stare
at them CU then you get a tattoo but
anyway uh
so in the text it means you're met you
should have meditation companions it
says very good it said especially
beginners and it said at least three of
you together would be good but then it
said uh they should be heavy weights
right they should be serious people
serious hard hard I like to call it
hardcore
practitioners and if they're not then
they're just going to waste your time
you know they're going to drag you down
I they had a rule in my my co I played
tennis in high school there was a debate
whether it was a Varsity Sport or not
because it was too wimpy uh but
uh yeah then the coach during season the
coach had a rule that you you were not
allowed to play tennis with anyone who
wasn't better than you it was a rule you
know especially not
girls uh so you know he just had a rule
that you couldn't you if you played
anybody you had to play somebody better
than you during the season you know and
it's kind of like that with meditation
you shouldn't be meditating with people
who are not serious it's good to
meditate with others but if they're if
they're not disciplined and and they're
not working hard then they're going to
just make you lazy you know so uh when I
say home
practice uh it's good to to do home must
learn to do home practice and hopefully
you could make a connection with some
people that you could meditate with that
you could practice with but what I
wanted to say was don't wait for them
you know like you could say let's meet
at 9:00 on Wednesday and if they're not
there by 9:05 then start meditating okay
and uh and if they're consistently not
show up then just stop and and do it on
you know you have to be selfrunning okay
you you have to in the end you have to
self-run your yoga your meditation and
your study and you can't wait for other
people and your book okay uh even if
nobody else is doing their you get out
your book and you do it
okay
uh while we're on the subject what was
the last one n
j
huh yeah you need your N means Yogi you
need your Yogi stuff Yogi stuff Yogi
stuff means
uh your poster with the notes on
it okay you you need your new notes okay
that's why the teacher went through the
the whole class thing was that you would
be prepared so the Yogi's Necessities or
no Yogi's what do you call yo can mean
Furniture in a house it can mean your
clothes the stuff you need to be what
you are uh so Yogi stuff is your
training and you have to have with you
your your reference your notes your
poster your you know what you learn and
it has to be ready uh someone has to
have trained you and that's the last I
think it's five I'm not
mistaken maybe I missed one I don't
think so okay uh so we were
at uh G jopa and what I wanted to say
was so you have by this time that is
achieved by
self-motivated practice right
um is this more irritating for you to
hear my
or should I clip it on here and you
can't hear
me you like the clip
thing let's have a vote how many you go
for the clip all
right problem is I find myself talking
like this and okay uh okay we'll go for
the
clip I have this theory that the big
exclamation things wake people up uh but
anyway uh
so the now we're ready to talk about the
one the first of the four modes okay the
states of mind okay we had what we had
nine levels six Powers four states of
Mind five problems eight fixes okay so
uh now we got to our first state of mind
the first two of the nine levels are
achieved by something called DDE dupa
say Jim
Jim
Jim Jim is a tough word inet J means
uh
uh there's no English word that's exact
it it means
uh concentrated conscious effort
concentrated conscious effort okay Jim
okay Jim j
means uh the first two levels require
some sort
of
uh concentrated effort on your part to
get to get into them okay so to get to
the place where you are on the object
like a fly or you are on the object
briefly those first two levels require
some
rather growth and what do you
call um uh considerable mental
effort okay it's not at all natural and
it's not at all fun and it's not at all
a flow like for the first two
levels when you're starting your
meditation it's it's like starting a
cold
car okay it's like it's going to take
some work to get your mind down into
meditation so Jima
means engaging only with difficulty
something engage deing with difficult
concentration it's an effort to get
started that's a my that implies
something later which is
what yeah later it's going to become
much more easy you know be more of a
what do you call that IND Grove or flow
okay all
right uh I'm going to go back to the
poster cool so I'm at number
[Music]
10 oh okay d means I'm at number 10 okay
the elephant has a uh
yam all
right that's very
significant uh
uh it says D from this point
[Music]
on H Jo okay so but the Tibetan is very
what do you call it they over in it you
can't read it
uh it says from this point on the the
head of the elephant will start to
become more white okay the Blackness
will recede from the elephant's
head uh and that represents that two
qualities of meditation are increasing
at this point say
s Nature
Nature Nature
Nature I'll start with nature okay
naturea
means uh fixation your ability to keep
your mind on the object okay your
ability to stay on the
object and then CA means Clarity okay
the condition of CH cha means condition
okay cell means clear like means clear
light right and then uh N means to stay
so nature is pretty basic just that
you're still on the object all right the
mind is still in the
object in the first two levels I like
this this is good for
in the first two levels of
uh I think I have some seed for this
from my P in the first two levels of uh
meditation uh is the N More or Less off
and see less right so the time off the
object is more than the time on the
object so nature is there nature is
there but it's not much okay then cell
chop means
Clarity it's a very common error in the
in the study of meditation that uh
people
mistake Clarity to mean the clearness of
the object so Richard talked yesterday
about the clarity of the face and he
said it got fuzzy at points that's not
what this Clarity means okay there there
is that
Clarity um with meaning how how clear is
the object right but in the study of
meditation when you talk about clarity
you're talking about the bright-eyed
bushy tailed nature of the attention the
quality of the attention so it's a
quality of the attending mind and not a
quality of the object you see so you're
not saying do you see your teacher's
eyes do you see your teacher's eyebrow
hairs or do you see their irises it
doesn't mean that Sela Clarity in the
study of meditation means is your mind
like engaged and happy and fresh okay I
like to call it freshness sometimes is
your mind like fresh and perky perky
okay on you have ccha when you're
reading your favorite book a really good
book a page Turner has Sela what they
call you can't you can't stop reading
you have to keep turning pages right you
stay up till 2 a.m. reading the book
there's this Sela there's this bright
brightness of the mind or when you're
looking at your favorite movie or stuff
like that those are like
SSH so at this point at Point number 10
uh the nature and the ca are getting
stronger and the and the the head is
turning white the Blackness is receding
what was the Blackness of the
elephant dullness okay so sea and NAA
are fighting the dullness here
okay okay I'm going to go on to number
11 then we're going to meditate a bit uh
number 11 says
do let
me okay uh
do
so
say
means
means objects of of the senses okay
objects of the senses with a negative
connotation daa
means
uh attached to the Starbucks coffee or
something daa means desire okay so
objects of the senses but with a
negative connotation like attachment
to to to taste attachment to sounds like
over attachment to music over attachment
to Donuts that's a d okay so
do and then uh
G GBA means
uh agitation but in a special sense
which
was towards something you want toward
something you like okay so you can also
get agitated mentally about someone you
don't like but that's not what agitation
means in the study of
meditation okay so agitation so
do five objects of the senses with with
regard to uh meditation as as objects to
which your senses will be drawn away
from your object of meditation so try to
meditate with someone sticking uh
McDonald's french fries under your nose
you know it's not possible like like
they talk about
what's what's that
mean
what's yeah
something meditation CMA means Cactus
Thorn we had it
it okay what's that
mean what's the sentence
mean yeah sounds are the cactus thorn of
meditation meaning they ruin your
meditation
automatically as if someone opened the
door while we were
meditating by the way if you come late
to
meditation uh don't open the door till
you see us break the meditation okay uh
or just don't come late it's better
[Laughter]
uh in the monastery they use an electri
cord okay and I'll tell you it don't
feel good uh okay so anyway uh so what
is what he's saying is that this is cool
okay he's got traditional
representations of the five objects of
the senses which you normally see in
tonas as being offered to the llama in
the picture okay but he's rip them off
of that context and put them in this
context it's kind of cool so here you
have
uh you have it in the hard Su
right what is
it right su su means the mirror
represent because a mirror reflects all
the visible objects in the world you
turn a mirror on anything and then that
object jumps into the glass right so the
mirror
represents uh attractive objects of the
eye like don't meditate don't put an
alter clock on your altar that looks
like that with the
Paisley and then meditate in front of it
you know because there's this thing you
kind of crack your eyes and then
suddenly this Paisley is jumping at you
okay and then the Mind goes to that
object you see the mind if if in front
of your eyes you have a some people
meditate better with their eyes half
open okay like the like this and they
look down but if you're going to try it
that way which can be good if you tend
to get sleepy okay do that but but put a
very plain colored object solid color in
front of your eyes and because if
there's any kind of a design then your
eye will be will be caught and that's
the meaning of the mirror okay the eye
being caught by by visible things
okay then that these are Ting shock say
thing shock what's thing
shock those things on
string those are thing shot okay so they
got two thing shots
here which is object they're going in
the hard seure way right ey ear nose
Tong body
uh eyes
ear where is
no oh right here
okay yeah there's a crunch
cell right around number eight 16 right
above number 16 there's a
con and in Tibet is traditional to put
water in it and put saffon in the water
okay in the opening of the con shell so
uh that represents
what Aromas of fragrances I I find uh
smells more distructive and sound you
know it's there's some meditation
centers I know that that prohibit uh
perfume for example I find it or or
Donuts we were
doing we did a hot yoga class in where
taipe and it's just over a Yow
shop which is like a Duncan Chinese
Dunkin Donut and and it it just seeps
you the flooor and you can't concentrate
okay uh and
I then
uh these are two
peaches okay Gumble Gumble and uh it
means taste okay distraction by taste
personally I like to brush my teeth
before I
meditate you know if you don't if you
like you eat something sweet and then
you meditate it can actually distract
you I think uh and then you to call the
numu numu means uh a bolt of varasi silt
okay which would mean
what yeah some objects of the touch okay
so those are the five objects of the
senses okay he's put them in the
picture and and these
represent uh potential candidates for
agitation potential candidates for
agitation those five objects of the
senses
yeah uh a bolt of silk to the to the
left number
10 so
uh I I think hopefully you're you're
you're withdrawn from the Cent senses
right hopefully your mind is withdrawn
from this objects of the senses during
meditation if they're not then you're
going to get distracted okay your mind
will
go are they could they be yiki could
they be
Dadu what's Dadu
dhad is
the is the object of the Mind these are
the objects of the five senses dhad is
the object of the six sense which is the
m could these exist in the
Dharma yeah there's a famous thing you
know all physical objects are divided
into two the outside ones and then the
the imagined one so if you're dreaming
about a maple covered donut that's also
okay got it this object of the senses it
doesn't doesn't mean you're smelling
french fries during meditation if you're
thinking about the taste of a
Whopper then uh that also will distract
you to the dhad S the ones that are just
imagined all right we're going to do a
little
meditation watch your breath
the mind is tied to the breath and
nothing else there's no other connection
to any other
object e
go to the golden
room the feeling of the light is very
soft friendly warm like a Christmas tree
and see the sky the Blue Sky out the
window
can see the m
across the valley
and your heart teacher comes to sit with
you and you look up into their
face your eyes need now just stay there
be be satisfied be happy be contented
with nothing more than that just their
eyes on your eyes with
love and stay quiet and contented in the
golden
room e
just be content to stay with your
teacher side you don't need anything
more this is sustenance for your mind
and
all
e
e e
and then slowly come
out
come it's good you're doing good I feel
you feeling concentration right feels
good feels good in the room I will just
keep going deeper and deeper and you
know more frequent okay
uh General if you can't sit in a room
quietly for five minutes without doing
anything you're going to have trouble
meditating
okay uh and it's a modern disease right
I don't know if it's a modern maybe it's
always been that way but uh people are
just hyper you know es I think computers
have really
you know I was one of the first people
to buy I bought a laptop an army
laptop had two floppy disc drives one
had the program one
had and it was
$5,000 and
uh and I'm not sure there they're a good
thing okay but anyway uh we have to
balance that with meditation you know so
generally if you can reach a point where
you can sit in a room quietly by
yourself without picking up a book or
turning on the Internet or listening to
music can you just sit quietly in a room
by yourself for even just five minutes
and just be contented and enjoy your
life uh and not in a lazy way okay not
like in a what do you call
it lassitude or something you know not
laying around but bright and engaged and
happy and
present uh without a laptop or your cell
phone that's a sign that your meditation
is getting better okay and if you can't
do
that just on a normal basis you're not
going to be meditating well I don't
think so also the condition of your room
reflects your meditation we went to
China we went to
juhi and uh we went to a special school
and they want to put The Diamond Cutter
into the universities Beijing University
and normal university and
some other universities they want to put
Diamond Cutter courses then they showed
us the Psychiatry Department psychology
department and they had sand boxes and
I've never seen them they're they're
waist high boxes and they have sand in
them and then there on the wall there
are shelves of uh Toy Soldiers dinosaurs
little
Buddhas uh you know
SpongeBob everything that you could
imagine you know little houses and trees
and then children come in and they can
Contour the sand anywhere they want and
then they go to the wall and there's
thousands of little figurines and then
they take like the army guys or they
take cars and and then they build a
scene in the sandbox and it's a
therapy uh and Christine Walsh was very
familiar with it and so they were like
freaked out because they were very
impressed but
um she uh but you could they had photos
of all the children standing in front of
their own creation and it was just like
seeing somebody's
room uh you walk into someone's house
and you say where's your room and they
show you to their room and then you can
see the state of their meditation in the
sandbox of their room you know if
everything's just random and scattered
around and and uh you know then the the
mind the state of mind is done it's a
reflection of your state of mind the S
it's a Sandbox your room is a Sandbox
right so I mean my teacher comes into my
house and they just start picking up
things you know like for 20 minutes it's
just this thing where they're putting
things away picking up things cleaning
things and you know when I studied uh
dance modern dance
Z so she would just she would not teach
the class if there was anything in the
room she would leave and you had to
still you had to pay for the class so if
there was a purse against the wall or or
a t-shirt hanging somewhere she would
she would take your money and leave you
know and uh so you so these are ways
that you can tell how your meditation is
what's the condition of your room and
and do you have the capacity to sit for
five minutes still quiet engaged and not
do anything else okay then these are
little measurements of how your mind
state is okay